And חנוכה שמח, Hanukkah Sameach, happy third day of חנוכה. Hanukkah. Today's
דף Daf is י"ז, Yud Zayin, seventeen, and we pick up at
the very bottom of ט"ז עמוד ב'. Tet Zayin Amud Bet. We're
dealing with the problem about if you not only enter the מקדש
Mikdash when you're טמא tamei doing a קרבן, korban, but even if
you stay there for the time and you do an act of
bowing down, even just bowing down on the knees, but if it's
officially an act of bowing down, meaning it's towards the west, towards
the קדש הקדשים, Kodesh Hakodashim, or if you hesitate the amount of
time it takes to do a full bowing down, which is like
three seconds or something. Anyway, so now we pick up at the
very bottom of ט"ז עמוד ב'. Tet Zayin Amud Bet. Doesn't take
longer to do a full bow down? I don't know, the גמרא
Gemara says how long how long it takes to read a פסוק.
pasuk. בעי רבא, Ba'ei Rava, רבא Rava asked: צריך שהייה למלקות או
אין צריך שהייה למלקות. Tzarich shehiya l'malkus o ein tzarich shehiya l'malkus.
This is all about a קרבן korban when it's בשוגג, b'shogeg, that's
the whole focus of our משנה. mishna. Let's say it was a
case of getting מלקות malkus and they warned the person, okay, and
they said: Don't wait, don't stay in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
you just became טמא! tamei! And he says: I don't care. And
they: you're gonna get מלקות. malkus. I don't care. So, after he
said those words, "I don't care," is he חייב chayav if he...
does he need to wait the full amount of time in order
to be חייב? chayav? Is that considered like you're actively staying? Now
there's two questions also. There's a question about that you don't get
מלקות malkus for לאו שאין בו מעשה. lav she-ein bo ma'aseh. So
there could be a question, you know, and sometimes we have it,
even passive is considered a continuation of an act. תוספות Tosafot discusses
this if you might remember we had in the גמרא Gemara מכות
Makkot about a person that is wearing כלאים kilayim and he has
an opportunity to like, you know, take it off and right, and
he doesn't take it off, and is the fact that he's keeping
it on the amount of time he could take it off and
put it back on considered like he put it off and put
it back on? And again, that's, you know, the question of is
the איסור issur of כלאים kilayim to put it on or to
wear it? But also, since he did an initial act of putting
it on, is keeping it on considered like an active type of
a thing, a continuing of the putting it on? This here is
a little different because here he became טמא tamei in the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, he never did an initial act of entering the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash טמא. tamei. But anyway, so one way of
conceptualizing this is, is that considered like he's actively staying? Is it
יש בו מעשה yesh bo ma'aseh or not? But the other way
is that, you know, at what stage is it? So the question
of יש בו שהייה, yesh bo shehiya, okay, you know, so is
that enough to give him מלקות malkus or not? Meaning you could
read if יש שהייה yesh shehiya to wait. Do you need to,
I think I might have misstated it the first time. Do you
need to wait, but then that's of course but then you wouldn't
get מלקות malkus immediately, I mean you were just warned and now
you gotta get yourself out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Clearly
you're not over in the first second. So the real question is
is that is waiting enough, since the person didn't actively enter the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, is just waiting and not running out enough
to deserve מלקות? malkus? And that again could as I said be
framed two ways. Number one, would we consider waiting an action? And
number two,
you know, maybe the מלקות malkus is for the לאו lav of
entering, is for the prohibition of entering, not for the issue for
the problem of staying. So let's take a look. Let me see.
Does the גמרא Gemara just say that waiting while being טמא tamei
is a problem? For קרבן. korban. The question is, we have a
tradition that that's true about קרבן, korban, right? Do we assume, or
we learn from a פסוק pasuk actually that you get כרת, kares,
and because we learn from the פסוק pasuk you get כרת, kares,
we can infer that there's a קרבן, korban, that was the earlier
discussion. But that doesn't say you could bring a קרבן korban without
doing an action, that doesn't say it would be considered an action
for מלקות malkus or that doesn't say that it would be the
transgression of the לאו lav that would deserve you מלקות, malkus, although
you would assume if there's a קרבן korban there's a לאו. lav.
So let's look at the גמרא's Gemara question.
בעי רבא: Ba'ei Rava: צריך שהייה למלקות או אין צריך שהייה למלקות.
Tzarich shehiya l'malkus o ein tzarich shehiya l'malkus. לקרבן גמירי שהייה למלקות
לא גמירי שהייה. L'korban g'miri shehiya l'malkus lo g'miri shehiya. For קרבן
korban we have this idea, not for מלקות. malkus. או דלמא, O
dilma, or do we say בפנים גמירי שהייה, bifnim g'miri shehiya, this
concept is true when it happens where טומאה tumah inside the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. You know, and we're not meaning it's about it's
about the nature of the violation. It's not a question about for
this הלכה. halacha. Right? Is it considered a violation to be waiting
around? So
the גמרא Gemara says תיקו. teiku. Okay.
Now, the funny thing is and what sort of made me misstate
it the first time is the phrase צריך שהייה, tzarich shehiya, do
you need שהייה? shehiya? sounds like the alternative is that you don't
need it and that you transgress immediately, right? Whereas I think that
the way that תוספות Tosafot is reading it and certainly like רש"י's
Rashi not so clear, okay, but רש"י Rashi also sounds like the
reading is not do you need it to transgress, but is it
sufficient to transgress? All right, so it's funny the way it's actually
being phrased.
You know, maybe you could say it the other way, you could
say like I said that if somebody, you know, קרבן korban is
somebody who's unintentional. If somebody's intentionally staying in, then maybe even if
they pause even for a second, right, that's the other way of
saying it, right? If I'm unintentional, so I haven't done something, you
know, so bad until like it's a what do you call it?
Like you know, if I you know if I accidentally became טמא
tamei you give me a little bit more latitude, right? And you
sort of like you know you give me time to go out
or whatever. But if I'm
willingly... which is, if that if somebody is intentionally violating, maybe you
don't even need to wait, obviously if he runs out, then he's
not intentionally violating. But if he's intentionally violating and staying, maybe even
for one second, that would get him מלקות. malkus. Okay, so that's
two ways to read it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. בעא רבא. Ba'ei Rava. So רבא Rava asked. תולה עצמו
באויר עזרה מהו. Toleh atzmo b'avir Azarah mahu.
Let's say the guy was actually like suspending himself. He was flapping
his arms and he was flying or something. I don't know. He
was climbing on the walls. He was suspending himself off the walls
of the עזרה. Azarah. What's the הלכה? halacha? And then for and
he waited the time it took to do השתחוויה. hishtachavaya. כי גמירי
שהייה שהייה דבת השתחוויה דלא בת השתחוויה לא גמירי. Ki gemiri shehiya,
shehiya de'vas hishtachavaya, d'la bas hishtachavaya lo gemiri.
Now this gets to real core of what's the idea of שהייה.
shehiya. Is the idea of שהייה shehiya that we consider it as
if you virtually did an act of bowing down? And therefore, you're
only transgress if you could have in theory bowed down during that
time. So when you're when you're hanging on the walls, you know,
when you're whatever, you're being Spider-Man. There you go. Spider-Man. So right,
so in that case, you can't do an act of bowing down.
So it's not just the waiting. It's the waiting translates into a
virtual bowing down. Okay, so in this case you would not be
you would not bring a קרבן. korban. או דילמא בפנים שהייה גמירי.
O dilma bifnim shehiya gemiri. Or is it a הלכה halacha just
of
any time that there's waiting inside similar to the phrase before, which
is sort of like a way of saying of this is just
the nature of this prohibition and we're not going to make distinctions.
לא שנא דבת השתחוויה ולא שנא דלא בת השתחוויה. Lo shna d'vas
hishtachavaya v'lo shna d'la bas hishtachavaya. Doesn't matter whether it's fit for
bowing down or not. תיקו. Teiku. We don't know. Okay, so we
have two questions. One is, is it just the amount of time,
or is it the amount of time that we convert view it
as you virtually bowed down? So if it's not physically possible to
bow down you would not transgress. Or and another question is, is
about do we apply this principle to מלקות? malkus? And again I
said that we can understand them in two ways. You could say
that if somebody is willfully staying, right? And they're not trying to
get up and they're saying I don't care, I'm going to stay
here even though I'm טמא tamei and so on, then you don't
need any minimum amount of time. Even doing it for a second
is an act of violation. I think that that's a very straightforward
way of reading רבא. Rava. But תוספות Tosafos seems to read it
the other way, which is is that maybe waiting is not sufficient.
Maybe the הלכה halacha of waiting was only said by a קרבן.
korban. Okay, and maybe that has to do with the fact that
you need to do an act in order to get מלקות. malkus.
Yes, Charlie. Back to the Spider-Man thing. I presume you're assuming the
עזרה Azarah is a רשות היחיד? reshus hayachid?
You mean like for ספק טומאה? safek tumah? Yeah, so that's I
don't know. I think I'm not sure that's true. I would have
to check on that. Okay, now take a look by the way
at תוספות Tosafos or about to understand this. Okay.
Oh, actually, I'm sorry. So okay.
For two things. First of all I just I I did תוספות
Tosafos a disservice because I see תוספות Tosafos explains it actually the
way I the way I was saying, not that whether שהייה shehiya
suffices, but whether you need שהייה. shehiya. See look at תוספות Tosafos
ואם צריך שהייה ve'im tzarich shehiya on י"ז עמוד א'. yud zayin
amud aleph. תוספות Tosafos says שהייה למלקות. shehiya l'malkus. הכא משמע דלקי
אשהייה. Hacha mashma d'lokei a'shehiya. You definitely would get lashes for שהייה.
shehiya. בלא קמיבעיא ליה אלא אי צריך שהייה כשיעור השתחווה או לא.
B'lo kamibaya lei ela i tzarich shehiya k'shiur hishtachavah o lo.
The only question is if you needed that amount, right, but certainly
if you were שוהה, shoheh, you would get מלקות. malkus. And then
that leads תוספות Tosafos into a discussion of why is it so
obvious? What about the fact that, you know, that you need an
act in order to get lashes? Okay, so so like you know
what they said, the last time I thought I was wrong I
was mistaken. So it goes back to the way I explained it
the first way after I started correcting my before I started correcting
myself, which is yes, the question is is that שהייה shehiya is
when the whole thing was unintentional, right, and therefore we could say
that we're not going to, you know, we're going to give you
a little latitude and until you wait a certain amount of time,
you're not violating. It's not considered like you are you actively staying
in, but if you're willfully staying there and you're saying you don't
care, then maybe you transgress for the first second. You maybe you
don't even need שהייה. shehiya. Okay, that's the question. Now by the
way, just for another clarification, look at the תוספות Tosafos before this.
צריך שהייה למלקות. Tzarich shehiya l'malkus. תוספות Tosafos says בטימא עצמו בשוגג
איירי. Betimei atzmo b'shogeg airi.
What happened was you didn't willfully מטימא metamei yourself. You're willfully staying
there, but you became טמא tamei בשוגג. b'shogeg. אבל אם היה שרץ
במקדש והזהירוהו שלא יטמא עצמו. Aval im hayah sheretz b'Mikdash v'hizhiruhu shelo
yitamei atzmo.
There was that שרץ sheretz or whatever they said, don't touch it
you'll be טמא, tamei, you're not allowed to be טמא tamei in
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And you said I don't care. בלא
שהה נמי מילקא לקי. B'lo shahah nami milka lakei.
Then it would be then clearly you would get מלקות. malkus. Then
you're getting מלקות malkus for the act of being מטימא metamei yourself.
Okay? So you got three scenarios. One scenario is you're טמא tamei
and they say don't walk into the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and
you walk in. Boom, מלקות. malkus. Okay, or they didn't warn you
and you walked in, boom, קרבן. korban. Act number two, they say
don't touch that שרץ sheretz in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and
you say you don't care and you touch it. Boom, מלקות. malkus.
Okay, scenario number three, you touched a שרץ sheretz in the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, okay, you did not willfully touch it. Now you're
aware that you're טמא. tamei. Okay. So, you know, it's one scenario
is you were aware for a second and then you forgot, which
is a little bizarre,
and then you forgot and then you were like, you know, because
that's העלם טומאה, helem tumah, like you need some העלם, helem, you
forgot that it happened and then you waited long enough and then
you realize then you bring a קרבן. korban. That's like the case
of our משנה, mishnah, but it's a little bizarre, I don't know
if we even stopped to explain the bizarreness of that, that you
touch it and then you forget half a second later. But the
other scenario is you touched it, you didn't forget,
and people are telling you you better get out because you're going
to get
חייב מלקות, chayav malkus, if you don't get out right away you're
טמא tamei and you're staying in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and
you say I don't care, and you willfully are staying in. So
in that case the question is, because you're willfully staying in, do
you get מלקות malkus for the first second or do you need
שיעור שהייה shiur shehiya even when you're intentional? So that is the
first question that we ask. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues. There'd be no שרצים shratzim if like you know, a little
זבוב... zvuv... I know, but maybe some eagle flying above dropped something.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, I don't know what
to tell you. בעי רב אשי, Bei Rav Ashi, so those were
רבא's Rava's questions. Now רב אשי Rav Ashi
asked: טימא עצמו במזיד מהו? Timei atzmo bemezid mahu? Now you're מטמא
metamei yourself willfully. Now that sounded like what תוספות Tosafos just said
was definitely חייב, chayav, but let's see what it sounds like in
the גמרא. Gemara. באונס גמירי שהייה במזיד לא גמירי שהייה. Be'ones gemiri
shehiya bemezid lo gemiri shehiya. Is it that you need שהייה shehiya
when the טומאה tumah became unintentional, but when it was willful you're
חייב chayav right away, similarly like willfully staying after you became טמא,
tamei, willfully touching you're חייב chayav right away. או
דלמא, O dilma, again it's also a little bit of a question
which is are we talking about that you're for קרבן korban or
are we talking about for מלקות? malkus? It's a little vague. You
would assume that since it's במזיד bemezid it's for מלקות, malkus, but
we'll talk about that in a minute. או דלמא O dilma or
do you say בפנים גמירי שהייה
לא שנא באונס ולא שנא במזיד? Bifnim gemiri shehiya lo shena be'ones
velo shena bemezid? No, this is a הלכה halacha about טומאה tumah
when you become טמא tamei in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and
it doesn't matter what the context is, whether it's whether you became
טמא tamei intentionally or unintentionally, you always need שהייה shehiya in order
to be חייב. chayav. So the גמרא Gemara says תיקו, teiku, we
don't know. Now, what's the case? Since it's talking about במזיד, bemezid,
you would think the issue is do you get מלקות malkus for
being מטמא metamei yourself במזיד, bemezid, which is a very reasonable question.
Of course, the answer presumably should be yes, you wouldn't need שהייה
shehiya if you willfully were מטמא metamei yourself, which is what תוספות
Tosafos said before. What תוספות Tosafos said before you definitely do get
מלקות, malkus, they can't explain the גמרא's Gemara's question that way. So
let's look at this תוספות: Tosafos: טימא עצמו במזיד מאי. Timei atzmo
bemezid mai. תוספות Tosafos says: צריך לומר דבשעה שטימא
עצמו לא ידע שהיה במקדש. Tzarich lomar desha'ah shetimei atzmo lo yada
shehayah beMikdash. So תוספות Tosafos says it's still talking about a קרבן.
korban. If you knew you were in the מקדש Mikdash and you
were מטמא metamei yourself במזיד, bemezid, boom, you definitely get מלקות. malkus.
The question is you forgot you were in the מקדש Mikdash and
you knew you were touching the שרץ sheretz and becoming טמא, tamei,
and then the question is in that scenario, so for תוספות Tosafos
it's still about a קרבן. korban. You're not willfully violating, you're willfully
טמא tamei but not willfully violating, and therefore that's the question of
do you even need the שהייה shehiya for that scenario? So we
have a lot of different types of variations. All right, do you
need it
if you're willfully מטמא metamei yourself and you know you're in the
מקדש Mikdash according to תוספות Tosafos then you obviously get מלקות. malkus.
If you did not willfully מטמא metamei yourself but you're willfully staying
in the מקדש, Mikdash, then the question is do you need שהייה
shehiya to get מלקות malkus or do you get מלקות malkus right
away the first second you're willfully staying? And then the third scenario
תוספות Tosafos reads as a קרבן, korban, you're willfully מטמא metamei yourself
but you don't realize you're in the מקדש, Mikdash, and the question
is do you bring a קרבן? korban? And for him, therefore, the
question is in that case since we're talking about a קרבן korban
do you definitely need שהייה shehiya or do we say maybe you
don't because you were willfully מטמא metamei yourself? Yes, Charlie. So there's
another case where you're going to get טומאה tumah in the עזרה,
azarah, which is you try to שחט shecht an animal and you
screw up which makes the animal נבלה. neveilah. Right, and that animal
needs to be removed, and someone has to remove it, and he's
doing it deliberately. That's a good point. You're right, that's a very
good point. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
All right, so those were some fun sort of variations. בעי רב
אשי, Bei Rav Ashi, now רב אשי Rav Ashi has another variation.
נזיר בקבר. Nazir bekaver.
Now, how about you're a נזיר, nazir, you could also ask about
a כהן kohen who's in a cemetery. Now, you would have to
say since before we were saying it might be a difference if
you were מטמא metamei yourself willfully or not, you'd have to say
like רש"י Rashi says, they were bringing this guy in in a
box and they were suspending the box in a way in which
he was being able to be in a cemetery and not become
טמא, tamei, and then somebody ripped the top off the box or
the bottom of the box collapsed and then he found himself, I
don't know, he was in a plane and the plane was crashing
and he jumped out with a parachute and he wound up landing
באונס be'ones in the בית הקברות. beis hakevaros. So he got into
the בית הקברות beis hakevaros without willfully entering in, or he was
chasing after a deer
and he turned... or whatever, he's in the בית הקברות. beis hakevaros.
It was unintentional. Okay. And now some and now the question is
right, does he need שהייה? shehiya? Now the שהייה shehiya here is
not for
the קרבן korban because the קרבן korban you bring is not for
becoming טמא. tamei. If a נזיר Nazir becomes טמא, tamei, he brings
a קרבן korban for not for the עבירה aveira of becoming טמא,
tamei, he would bring it even if he became טמא tamei באונס.
be'ones. He brings it in order to restart his נזירות. neziros. So
we're definitely not dealing with the issue of קרבן korban here and
there's no קרבן korban for the עבירה aveira of becoming טמא. tamei.
We're dealing with the idea of getting lashes. So it's similar to
the question before about whether you need you get for מלקות, malkos,
are you טמא tamei and you're willfully staying, do you get lashes
immediately or only after you you you wait the amount of שהייה?
shehiya? Okay, because by the way, just just realize it'll be a
little bizarre that the amount of time that we would clock you
by by a נזיר Nazir would be the amount of time to
do a prostration. Like to say that in the עזרה azara and
in טומאה tumah and it's like you did an עבודה avodah when
you were טמא tamei and therefore the reason you're getting lashes it's
because you had enough time to be present and to do something
in the עזרה azara that would be meaningful, okay, that would be
make sense in the עזרה azara that we would look at the
time to bow down. Why should we look at it here? So
let's take a look. בעי אמר רבא, Ba'ei amar Rava, נזיר בקבר,
Nazir bekever, בעי שהייה למלקות ba'ei shehiya lemalkos או אינו צריך? o
einu tzarich? בפנים גמירי שהייה, Bifnim gemiri shehiya, in the עזרה azara
now you really understand the context of the idea of בפנים. bifnim.
Before we weren't understanding so much why it was emphasized that, okay,
but בפנים, bifnim, the point about this amount of time makes sense
in the עזרה. azara. בחוץ לא גמירי שהייה, Bachutz lo gemiri shehiya,
not outside. או דילמא באונס גמירי שהייה. O dilma be'ones gemiri shehiya.
No, maybe it's the הלכה halacha for just when it hap- the
טומאה tumah happened באונס. be'ones. So now the point is, when when
do we say you've done something wrong? The whole situation plopped itself
on you, okay, and you know, so when can when can we
say that you've done something substantial enough to like we can measure
that you entered into the בית הקברות beis hakevaros when you were
טמא. tamei. How do we measure that you stayed? What does it
mean to stay, right? So like if you think about it when
you eat something, it's not enough to eat a tiny bit to
transgress, you need to eat a כזית, kezayis, right? So so there's
a logic that there's a שיעור, shiur, an amount of staying that
is considered like because the situation, you know like I said, just
sort of fell on you. So what does it mean that you've
done something wrong, that you're deserving מלקות, malkos, you actively stayed? So
that would make sense that we would need. Now why the amount
of time should be the amount of time to bow down, who
knows? Okay, but anyway, that's the question. Okay. או דילמא באונס גמירי
שהייה, O dilma be'ones gemiri shehiya, whenever it happened באונס, be'ones, in
order to make what you're doing considered an act, that requires
שהייה, shehiya, לא שנא בפנים ולא שנא בחוץ, lo shna bifnim velo
shna bachutz, it doesn't matter in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash out
of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and the גמרא Gemara ends with
תיקו, teiku, we don't know. I see this hands up before I
pick up the hands I want to say, תוספות Tosafos asks a
very important question which is very relevant for כהנים, kohanim, which תוספות
Tosafos says, I don't understand, once you're in the בית הקברות beis
hakevaros you're not doing another transgression by staying in the בית הקברות
beis hakevaros because your level of טומאה tumah is not increasing. Meaning
when you're in the מקדש Mikdash and you're טמא, tamei, the nature
of the violation is is that your טומאה tumah
is violating the מקדש Mikdash and your staying in the מקדש Mikdash
is maintaining that state of violation. You need to remove the offensive
thing from the מקדש, Mikdash, right? That's why staying in the מקדש
Mikdash when you're טמא tamei is a problem. But when you are
a נזיר, Nazir, the problem is not that you're staying in the
בית הקברות beis hakevaros that you're the problem. The problem is you're
becoming טמא, tamei, but as long as you're there right on top
of the קבר, kever, you're not becoming any more טמא tamei by
staying there, right? So I mean, I understand at a certain emotional
level, a נזיר Nazir in a בית הקברות beis hakevaros is like
offensive, they don't belong together, you got to get him out. Okay,
but הלכתית, halachically, the problem is you're becoming טמא. tamei. So תוספות
Tosafos says, how you more becoming טמא tamei by just staying there
longer? And this is very relevant for a question of like if
a כהן kohen is טמא tamei while a כהן kohen is sort
of like car- you know for father let's say or mother, you
know you- he's obviously allowed to become טמא, tamei, he brings the
sort of, you know, the coffin into the בית הקברות beis hakevaros
or whatever, you know, so then the question is he's like he's
not a problem if he goes over other קברות kevaros or other
types of things because it's not like increasing the level of טומאה.
tumah. Interesting question comes after the burial, how does he have to
get himself out of the בית הקברות beis hakevaros and the fact
that he's טמא tamei today but he's not actively touching a מת
meis and there's all those distinctions. But anyway תוספות Tosafos raises that
important point that it's one thing in the מקדש, Mikdash, the you
know the טומאה tumah there is a continued violation and it has
to be removed. Whereas here if you're already טמא, tamei, what is
the continued violation? Okay, Charlie you had a question then Michael, yeah.
Yeah, I just forgot my business.
Okay, Michael. My question is this: the differences between קידה, kida, השתחויה
histachavaya and you know, prostrating? Does that ever נפקא מינה nafkamina on
יום כיפור Yom Kippur like what we're supposed to be doing, the
people like ground this גמרא? Gemara? Well
I mean, you know, well כורעים ומשתחוים, korim umishtachavim,
I mean yeah, I mean people do I do it בפישוט ידיים.
bifishut yadayim. I do too, but I see most People just do
it on their knees? People don't go down like that? I've seen
people just, meaning פישוט ידים pishut yadayim means like you're like a
line, right? Doesn't that mean that? Not clear because that might be
קידה kida because that's like getting your face totally against the ground.
But anyway, it's just a מנהג minhag Michael, it's not a הלכה
halacha by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, yes? פישוט ידים pishut yadayim could
just mean, anyway this is yesterday's דף. daf. Yes. What isn't...
doesn't רמי Rami mean that your legs are out? Oh, it's interesting.
So then what's the difference between that and קידה? kida? If you're
totally flat and your face... אף על פי af al pi קידה
kida was that you... well that's what they said, that no one
else can do it other than רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel because you
actually don't bend your knees, you just put your face... Okay, I
don't know, anyway that's yesterday's דף. daf. Yes, the comparison to eating,
there's
while you have to have a certain שיעור shiur in order to
get punished, we also hold חצי שיעור אסור מן התורה. chatzi shiur
assur min ha-Torah. Right. But is there a comparable thing for time?
Right, so that's an interesting question. The גמרא Gemara here is focused
on this punishment or the consequence, קרבן korban or the מלקות. malkos.
Okay. Why is it נזיר nazir becomes טמא tamei is it גופו?
gufo? Well,
because if...
yeah,
it's not so... I don't want to get into it. Yeah, I
understand, it's not so clear, you're right, but I don't want to
get into it. Okay, בלא בארוכה חייב ובקצרה פטור. ba lo b'arucha
chayav u-biktzara patur.
Now let's say, now so what we now focus on the amount
of time or the act of השתחויה. hishtachavaya. But the other point
is, did he take the short route out or the long route
out? Okay, so he became here whatever, okay, טמא tamei here, okay,
if he goes a straight line, but if he sort of went
like that, okay, then he transgresses. If he takes the short route
out he's חייב, chayav, the long route out... well I thought there
were actually two doors, right? Weren't there? Whatever, it doesn't matter, whatever.
Any longer route he's חייב. chayav. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, קצרה שאמרו אפילו
עקב בצד גודל ואפילו כל היום כולו. Ketzara she-amru afillu akev b'tzad
godel v'afillu kol hayom kulo. So רבא Rava says it's very fascinating.
רבא Rava says, okay, here is you're standing and you're doing nothing,
but as long as you are actively walking and as long as
you're doing the short route, you can take the whole day to
walk it. So you can go like this: very slowly, I'm getting
there. And you can talk to someone along the way... but if
you pause, then we measure it by שהייה shehiya and you're חייב.
chayav. If you take a long route even if you run it,
you're חייב. chayav. Okay, the הלכה halacha is pausing is one thing
and short route is another, as long as you're actively walking and
the short route is not measured by... we don't give you a
time, it's just you have to walk out the short route. Okay,
ואפילו כל היום כולו. v'afillu kol hayom kulo. So
בעי רבא, ba'ei Rava, so רבא Rava asks. שהיות מהו שיצטרפו? shehiyot
mahu she-yitzatrefu? Let's say, okay, we decided that the שיעור shiur of
שהייה shehiya was three seconds. Okay, was three seconds. So now I'm
going to wait a second, I'm going to start walking, short route.
Wait a second, start walking. Do they combine? Wait a second, okay,
so it's not one period of three seconds. Do they combine? Okay,
מהו שיצטרפו? mahu she-yitzatrefu? דתפשוט ליה מדידיה, d'tifshot lei mi-didei, why can't
he figure it out from his own ruling? Why? Because he himself
ruled that you can go very slowly as you're walking out. So
I just already gave you the answer. But the גמרא Gemara thinks
if you're going very slowly isn't that a lot of pauses? So
the גמרא Gemara says no, התם דלא שהה. hatam d'lo shaha. That's
going extremely slowly but never stopping and pausing. I want to know
if he took a little tiny bit of breaks. Okay, so we
don't know the answer. בעי מיניה אביי מרבא, Ba'ei minei Abaye me-Rava,
now אביי Abaye asked רבא. Rava. אביי Abaye is... this question will
sort of also answer... will imply an answer to רבא's Rava question.
בלא בארוכה שיעור קצרה מהו? ba lo b'arucha shiur ketzara mahu?
So רבא Rava took it for granted that it's about which path
you take, not the amount of time you take.
אביי Abaye asks exactly that question. When we say the short path
or the long path, do we say if he would go this
way it would take five seconds, if he would go this way
it would take ten seconds? And now the real or... or you
know, or maybe I guess the real point is anything that's more
than five seconds. If he would go this way it would take
five seconds. So now the rule is he can't take more than
five seconds getting out. If he's a fast runner and can do
that the long route in five seconds, he's safe. If he goes
the short route and takes more than five seconds, he transgresses. אביי
Abaye is asking what רבא Rava takes it for granted that it's
defined by the route, not the time. אביי Abaye asks that question:
is it defined by the time it takes to do the route
or is it defined by which route you take? Okay, you could
tell they were having fun. So בעי אביי מרבא, ba'ei Abaye me-Rava,
so אביי Abaye asks from רבא. Rava. בלא בארוכה שיעור קצרה. ba
lo b'arucha shiur ketzara. You did the long route but you did
it so fast, you're a good runner, in the time it takes
to do the short route. מהו? mahu? What's the הלכה? halacha? שיעור
גמירי? shiur gemiri? That is it really about the amount of time?
וכי בא לו בארוכה שיעור קצרה פטור, v'chi ba lo b'arucha shiur
ketzara patur, so if you do the long route but the amount
of time for the short route you're exempt? או דילמא דווקא גמירי?
o dilma davka gemiri? No, or it's like רבא Rava assumed, it's
not about the time, it's about the route, בארוכה. b'arucha. The long
one you're חייב chayav *chayav*, the short one you're פטור *patur*. It's
about the route you take, not the amount of time. אמר ליה
*Amar lei*: לא ניתנה ארוכה להידחות אצלו *Lo nitna arucha lehiddachot etzlo*.
You cannot, you know, the long one cannot be pushed off in
favor of the short one, which basically sounds like he's saying the
way רש"י Rashi *Rashi* reads it, the long one you're always going
to be חייב chayav, *chayav* for. Even if you do it fast,
okay? So that sounds like what רבא Rava *Rava* was assuming. It's
not the amount of time it takes to do the short one,
it's the route. Okay? So
if you do the short route and you take a long time,
you're fine. You do the long route and you take a short
time, you transgress. Sounds like we're getting back to רבא Rava *Rava*'s
idea that it goes by the route and not the amount of
time. Wait, let's keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this. So מתקיף לה רב זביד *Matkif lah Rav Zevid*. רב
זביד *Rav Zevid* asked on this. אלא דקיימא לן טמא tamei? ששימש
במיתה היכי משכחת לה *Ela dekayma lan tamei sheshimesh bemita heichi mishkachat
lah*? So we have a הלכה halacha *halacha* that if somebody is
טמא tamei. *tamei*, a כהן kohen *Kohen*, and he does עבודה avodah.
*avoda* in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*, he's חייב מיתה
בידי שמים chayav misa bidei shamayim. *chayav mita bidei shamayim*. Not מיתת
בית דין beis din *mitat beis din*, מיתה בידי שמים misa bidei
shamayim *mita bidei shamayim*. Okay, and now מיתה בידי שמים misa bidei
shamayim. *mita bidei shamayim* is different than if you stay in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash? *Beis Hamikdash* where you're חייב chayav כרת kares.
*chayav kares*. So רב זביד *Rav Zevid* assumes—now why he has to
assume this is not clear—that there's a scenario where you are a
כהן kohen *Kohen* who does עבודה avodah *avoda* in the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash* when you're טמא tamei. *tamei*, you only get
מיתה בידי שמים *mita bidei shamayim* and you don't get כרת karet
*kares* for staying in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beis Hamikdash* as
a טמא tamei *tamei* person, because it only says מיתה *mita*, and
he assumes that מיתה *mita* suggests that's the only punishment you get.
So what is the scenario that you were able to do an
עבודה avodah. *avoda* in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beis Hamikdash* when
you were טמא tamei. *tamei* and not stay there long enough to
be חייב chayav, כרת karet *chayav kares*? Okay? You got it? Because
for the עבודה avodah *avoda* you're חייב מיתה בידי שמים chayav misa
bidei shamayim. *chayav mita bidei shamayim*, but aren't you staying long enough?
Aren't you חייב chayav כרת *chayav kares* as well? So היכי משכחת
לה *Heichi mishkachat lah*? אי דלא שהה shoheh *Ei dalo shahah*, if
the guy ran out, היכי עביד עבודה avodah *heichi avid avoda*? How
did he do the עבודה avodah. *avoda*? Where did he have the
time? אי דשהה *Ei deshahah*, so if he took the amount of
time that it takes to do the עבודה avodah. *avoda*, בר כרת
הוא *bar kares hu*, then it's not just מיתה *mita*, it's also
כרת *kares*. Now, why is that dependent on our earlier discussion about
the long route and the short route? Let's take a look. אי
אמרת בשלמא שיעורא גמירי *Ei amart bishlama shiura gemiri*, if the point
is short route—if the point is the amount of time it takes,
so you're only חייב chayav *chayav* if you spend more than the
amount of time it takes to do the short route, so משכחת
לה דאנחי נפשיה בקצרה ועביד עבודה avodah *mishkachat lah de'anchi nafshei bekatzara
ve'avid avoda*. So here's the idea. This short route is five seconds.
Okay? So then he says, well, we would understand that the real
הלכה halacha *halacha* here is five seconds. Okay? So therefore, you would
have a case that you did an עבודה avodah *avoda*—or let's say,
I don't know, the guy who's like way back here, okay, let's
say you've got a sort of, like, I don't know, move around
or whatever, and let's say it's 30 seconds. There are a lot
of people, who knows? Okay, so we've got now, we're putting you
on the clock. You've got 30 seconds, buddy. Okay, that's your short
route. Okay? So this guy's really fast. He שחט shacht *shacht* the
קרבן korban *korban*, you know, he's got the knife right there by
the neck of the קרבן korban *korban*, takes two seconds, he runs
here and he gets out within the 30 seconds. That would make
sense if it's about here. Okay? אלא *Ela*, but, אי אמרת דווקא
גמירי *ei amart davka
gemiri*, if the issue is short route and not the amount of
time it takes to do a short route, so היכי משכחת לה
*heichi mishkachat lah*? How do you find it? Now that's not exactly
clear because what's your problem? He still שחט *shacht* the קרבן korban
*korban* and then goes out the short route. What's the issue? So
the way רש"י *Rashi* explains it, right, you understand the question? Like
why should it matter? Right? So
the way רש"י *Rashi* explains it is the following: how, if you
say—how do you factor in the combination that we said short route
plus we said that you've got, you can wait שהייה shehiya
*shehiya*, let's get another one of the nice new pens that חנני
*Chanani* gave me.
Okay? You could have here, you have שהייה *shehiya*, and שהייה *shehiya*
is defined as we said, let's say three seconds, okay?
How do those two factors combine? All right? So the way רש"י
*Rashi* explains it is the following, is that if you say that
the idea of short route is to determine the amount of time,
then רש"י *Rashi* would say we would total the time. The short
route time is 30 seconds plus you're allowed to be שהה *shocheh*
up to three seconds, right, that's the כדי השתחוואה *kedai hishtachavaya*, remember
that? So your total amount of time, buddy, we're putting 33 seconds
on the clock, duh! Okay? And then we get the idea, right,
that we're assuming the עבודה avodah, *avoda*, let's say we assume the
עבודה avodah, *avoda* will take you, like, I don't know, seven seconds.
Okay? So then we understand it. You could say, all right, the
short route was 30 seconds. It's all about time. שהייה *Shehiya* is
three seconds. I got 33 seconds. This'll take me seven seconds, and
then I can rush out in the next thing in 25 seconds.
That makes sense. I figure, right, I can understand how you can
do the עבודה avodah *avoda* and get out in time. Everybody with
me? But if the short route is not about time... Then there's
just the following הלכה. halacha You have to take the short route
out and,
independent of having to take the short route out, you can't be
שהה more than three seconds. So now you got a problem, because
now it's going to take you more than three seconds to do
the עבודה. avodah. Okay, so that's why he says, if it's about
time, I get, you can combine this time with this time, do
the עבודה avodah and rush out. But if it's about take this
route and don't spend more than three seconds pausing, he says, it's
going to take you more than three seconds to do the עבודה.
So how does that work? All right. What's he doing the עבודה
if he knows he's טמא? tamei He told me he's טמא. tamei,
All right, he shouldn't be, but that's why he's חייב מיתה chayav
misa בידי שמים. Okay, but that's what we're trying to do. The
הלכה halacha is he's חייב מיתה chayav misa, and he wants to
know what's the scenario that he violates and is חייב מיתה, chayav
misa, but then doesn't violate spending too long in the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash which would also get him כרת. Okay, so if, again,
if you say you can combine the times and you got 33
seconds, I get it. He does this, takes seven seconds, rushes out
in 25 seconds, he's safe. But if it's take the short route
and don't do anything, pause anything for longer than three seconds, how
is he going to do the עבודה and not also be חייב
chayav for being in the בית המקדש? The גמרא Gemara says אלא
אי אמרת דווקא גמירה השתא משכחת לה. ela ei amart davka gemira
hashata meshakchas lah. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, says אביי, Abaye, מאי
קושיא, mai kushya, why is this difficult?
משכחת לה כגון דבא בקצרה והפך בצינורא. meshakchas lah kegon de'ba biktzara
vehapach betzinora. Basically, says, I don't get it, it's very easy. Why
is it so easy? Because, let's say here he is, he's not
down here, he's up here, he's at the top of the מזבח.
mizbeach. Okay, here we've got some fire, here we've got like a
קורבן korban sitting there and here's a little, here's a little like
a fork, a pitchfork that's up there that's for turning, thank you,
that's for turning the meat, for turning the meat over the קורבן.
korban. So what he does is, okay, there it is, it's burning
on the fire. So what he does is, fine, he's going to
run straight down here, go straight down, he's going to take the
shortest route. Okay, but as he's running out, he flips over the
קורבן korban on his way out. He didn't even have to pause
for a second. There you are, you're running, you turned over the
thing and you kept on walking. Even if it took a half
second, he still has three seconds to wait, he has the three
seconds to pause. So אביי Abaye says I get it, okay, והפך
בצינורא, vehapach betzinora, כדרב הונא, ked'Rav Huna, like רב הונא, Rav Huna,
דאמר רב הונא, de'amar Rav Huna, זר שהפך בצינורא חייב מיתה. zar
shehapach betzinora chayav misa. For a non-כהן kohen turned over with the
pitchfork like a meat of a קורבן korban so it would burn
better, חייב מיתה, chayav misa that's an עבודה. The same way putting
the fat and the entrails on the altar is an
עבודה. Okay, so then I mean not one of the classic four
עבודות, avodos, but whatever. Then also the,
then also an עבודה for a non-כהן kohen to be חייב chayav
מיתה בידי שמים. It's also an עבודה for a כהן kohen to
be חייב chayiv מיתה if he does it when he is טמא.
tamei Okay, so it's part of the burning of the fats and
entrails on the מזבח. mizbeach. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, גופא,
gufa, let's look at that statement. אמר רב הונא זר שהפך בצינורא
חייב מיתה. amar Rav Huna zar shehapach betzinora chayav misa. היכי דמי,
heichi dami, what's the case? אי דלא הפך לא מיאכלי, ei dela
hapach lo miachali, if the meat, if you wouldn't turn it over,
wouldn't
cook, wouldn't be consumed by the fire, because that's gotta burn up.
So פשיטא, pshita, of course, שחייב, she'chayav, like you did something that
was necessary, that was like putting it on the fire, without your
turning it over, it wouldn't have been consumed. ואי דלא הפך בהו
נמי מיאכלי, ve'ei dela hapach behu nami miachali, and if you say
that no, eventually the fire would have burnt it even had you
not flipped it over, so מאי קעביד, mai ka avid, why is
that an עבודה, why do you transgress? The thing would have happened
anyway, you didn't do anything that was necessary. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, לא צריכא, lo tzricha, you need it דאי לא הפיך
בהו מיאכלי בתרתי שעי, de'ei lo hapich behu miachali betarti sha'ei, if
you would not turn it over it would have taken two hours
to be burnt up, והשתא מיאכלי בחדא שעתא, ve'hashata miachali be'chada sha'ata,
and now because you turned it over it did, it took only
one hour. So it wasn't necessary, but it would have gotten done
eventually, but it was helpful, it speeded up the process. Okay, והא
קמשמע לן, ve'ha kamashman, this is teaching דכל קירובי עבודה עבודה היא.
de'chol keruvei avodah avodah hi. Anything that speeds up the עבודה, that
helps the עבודה get done quicker, even though it's not absolutely necessary,
is considered to be part of the עבודה. And enough for a
non-כהן kohen to get מיתה בידי שמים or a כהן kohen who
is טמא tamei to get מיתה בידי שמים. Yes, Charlie.
That's kind of a חידוש chiddush because it's not one of the
four עבודות. avodos. Well, yeah, but that's, but that's different. Meaning it's
not one of the classic four עבודות avodot to make a קורבן
כשר, korban kasher, which is שחיטה קבלה הולכה וזריקה. shechita kabala holacha
vezrika. But it is an עבודה of the things that are limited
to כהנים kohanim and only and prohibited against a non-כהן and also
similarly prohibited against a כהן who is טמא. tamei, Okay. On the
other question is we talk about shortest route and the way you
have it on the board is shortest route out of the עזרה,
azara, but it's also אסור assur to be טמא tamei or at
least some form of טומאה tumah in the הר הבית Har HaBayis
itself. Yeah, I mean, but
the חיוב, chiyuv, but the חיוב, chiyuv, these טומאות tumos are only
basically a problem in
the... You can still go on
הר הבית, Har HaBayis, right. But it's a good question. Okay, so
the גמרא gemara says like
this: אמר רב אושעיא, Amar Rav Oshaya, בעינא דאימא מילתא, Beina de'eima
milta, I want to say something, ומסתפינא מחברייא, umistafina mechavraya, but I'm
afraid about the reactions of my colleagues. Okay, it's very interesting. Sometimes
in a תשובה, teshuvah, if somebody wants to say something that's a
little bit innovative or radical or whatever, he would write לולי דמסתפינא,
lulei demistafina, if I were not afraid for the reaction from my
colleagues, I would say the following, and then he goes ahead and
says it. Which is like I'm acknowledging that this is a little
radical and I'm not, I'm saying it a little tentatively, but here
goes. Okay, so that's exactly what he's saying here. I want to
say something, but I'm afraid by the reaction of my colleagues. Here's
what I want to say: הנכנס לבית המנוגע דרך אחוריו ואפילו כולו
חוץ מחוטמו טהור. Ha'nichnas l'veit hamenuga derech achorav v'afilu kulo chutz mechotamo
tahor. If somebody goes into a house that has צרעת, tzara'at, okay,
and if you enter the house you're טמא, tamei so if you
were to go normally face, you know, front in, you know, with
your face facing it, then presumably you're חייב, chayiv you're, you know,
as soon as the majority of your body went in, then you've
entered into the house. It says הבא אל הבית, haba el habayit,
the person who enters into the house or to be defined as
entering when the majority of your body was in the house. But
he says if you're walking in backwards, even if a tiny part
of your body is outside of the doorway, like even like your
nose, like, you know, is still sticking out, facing outwards, and it's
not into the house, you have not, you're טהור. tahor.
You're not טמא tamei. because you haven't entered in. Now what's the
difference which way you enter in? So let's take a look. Okay,
ואפילו כולו חוץ מחוטמו, v'afilu kulo chutz mechotamo, his whole body except
for his nose, טהור, tahor, דכתיב, de'chtiv, והבא אל הבית, v'haba el
habayit, דרך ביאה אסרה תורה. derech bi'ah assra Torah. It's only if
you enter in in a natural way. Now why we're saying it
here is going to be relevant because we're going to connect it
to the בית המקדש in a minute. But anyway, so I want
to say that. Now why is that so crazy? It's a reasonable
thing to say, maybe, it says if you come, you have to
come naturally in a normal way. ומסתפינא מחברייא, Umistafina mechavraya, here's why
I'm afraid to say, of the reaction of my colleagues, because אי
הכי, ei hachi, they'll say back to me, כולו נמי. kulo nami.
So then why do you say he's טהור tahor only because his
nose is out? Even if he goes in 100% he should be
טהור tahor because he never officially entered in. He came in backwards.
Right, you understand the question? If you're only טמא tamei when you
come in naturally, normally, so then even if you come in, the
whole part of you comes in, you should be טהור. tahor. So
he says, I recognize the question, I don't have an answer, but
obviously when you're fully in you're טמא, tamei. I just don't know
a way to explain why. So comes רבא to his defense. So
אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
כולו לא גרע מכלים שבבית. kulo lo gara mikelim shebabayit. You know,
if you're, if you enter in totally, then you're טמא tamei not
for entering in the house, you're טמא tamei for being in the
house. And that's just like the vessels, the vessels that were in
the house didn't enter but they're טמא. tamei. So if you're fully
in, you're טמא tamei, for that reason. Okay, דכתיב, de'chtiv, ונטמא כל
אשר בבית. v'nitma kol asher babayit. Okay, everything in the house becomes
טמא. tamei So basically saying, you're right actually, you actually, if you
think about it, this might have been a good strategy, you know,
for who was it who was saying it, רב אושעיא. Rav Oshaya.
Like if you say something radical, everybody's going to jump on you.
If you say, I have an idea, but there's this one problem
with it that doesn't, can't figure out, then everybody will try to
figure out how to help you explain that idea. Okay, so anyway
he got רבא on his side. So anyway, but he says, here's,
you're טמא tamei when you do an act of entering, that's defined
as going in face first and the majority of your body, and
you would be טמא tamei if you were fully in the house,
like anything in the house, and that doesn't matter how you got
in. Okay, and either way you're טמא. tamei Now how is this
relevant to us? Let's take a look. תניא נמי הכי. Tanya nami
hachi. גגות הללו, Gagot hallalu, the roofs on top of the עזרה
Azara and the היכל, Heichal, okay, were not sanctified with the קדושה
kedusha of the היכל Heichal and of the עזרה. Azara. אין אוכלין
שם קדשי קדשים ואין שוחטין שם קדשים קלים. Ein ochlin sham kodshei
kodashim v'ein shochtin sham kodashim kalim. You can't eat there the holy
of holies, the holiest sacrifices, you can't שחט שלמים, shelamim, it does
not have
the קדושה kedusha of the עזרה Azara or of the היכל. Heichal.
Okay, it doesn't have the קדושה kedusha of the עזרה Azara or
of the היכל. Heichal. So because it doesn't have that קדושה, kedusha,
והטמא שנכנס דרך גגין להיכל פטור. v'hatamei shenichnas derech gagin l'heichal patur.
Now, so first of all, if somebody is on the roof here
and you're טמא, tamei you don't transgress for being on the roof
because you're not in the עזרה. Azara. The עזרה Azara is only
defined as the floor going up to the roof. But from the
roof on, the airspace is also like has the קדושה, kedusha, okay,
but you, right, we just talked before about guy suspended in the
air. That was only a question of could he bow down or
not. But the airspace has the קדושה, kedusha, but only going up
to the roof. Guy here is on the roof, he is not
violating being טמא tamei, in the עזרה, Azara, so he's still safe.
Then he crashes through the roof and lands down here. Okay, so
that's now what we're. That's what we're comparing it to the case
of the guy who walks in the house backwards. He didn't enter
naturally into the עזרה. azarah. He was safe when he was on
the roof and now he's crashed through and entered through the roof,
okay, that also he's not חייב chayav for entering the עזרה, azarah,
that's not an act of entering. All right. But כל שנכנס דרך
גגין והיכל פטור שנאמר ואל המקדש לא תבוא דרך ביאה אסרה תורה.
kol she-nichnas derech gaggin ve-heichal patur she-ne'emar ve-el ha-mikdash lo tavo derech
bia asrah torah.
Only if you enter in the natural way and in that way
it's similar to Rav Oshaya's point that entering means entering in naturally.
Of course if you now know that you're in the עזרה, azarah,
if you waited too long you would be חייב, chayav right? But
that would be a case but the act of entering, normally you're
חייב chayav, if you're already טמא tamei. the very moment you enter,
you transgress. Here, not. Because you have not entered the natural way.
But you would transgress, of course, going back to our earlier theme,
if you waited around. All right, now we do, yes, Charlie. So
today we would not be transgressing entering the עזרה azarah while טמא
if we were to be dropped from a helicopter? Exactly. But then
you transgress if you stayed around. By staying around, yeah, so we
could be there and then immediately leave. Exactly. Okay, so זו מצות
עשה שבמקדש שאין חייבין עליה. zo mitzvat aseh she-be-mikdash she-ein chayavin aleha.
Now
the משנה, mishnah, I wasn't here when you did the משנה, mishnah,
but the משנה mishnah does this weird turn. Okay, and I mean
this is so funny the way that all of these things are
such digressions from getting to our point about שבועות. shavuos. Okay, we
did this whole thing about טומאת מקדש tumas mikdash and what קרבן
korban and then what you're atoned for on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
and now we're dealing with we're still like how do you transgress
טומאה tumah now we get to some completely other הלכה halacha about
when is a בית דין beis din חייב chayav, for when they
rule... this is a הוריות Horayos discussion which we'll get to eventually.
If a בית דין beis din rules and says that you're allowed
to do something and you do it and it's a sin that's
that and they were making a mistake and it's a sin that
you get כרית kares for, then בית דין beis din brings a
קרבן korban. when most of ישראל Yisrael listens to them for their
bad ruling. But it would only be a type of a sin
that you would get כרית kares for if you did willfully and
bring a חטאת chatas for if you did unintentionally. And the משנה
mishnah says these and also the גמרא gemara says it's a type
of a scenario where there's a positive מצוה mitzvah associated with it
and a negative מצוה mitzvah associated with it. So the גמרא gemara
says even though the case of the מקדש mikdash is a sin
that you bring a קרבן korban for and a sin that there's
כרית kares and there's a negative מצוה, mitzvah, don't enter in, and
a positive מצוה mitzvah which is ישלחו מן המחנה, yishalchu min ha-machaneh,
send the טמא people out, if בית דין beis din ruled incorrectly
about this they would not bring a קרבן korban. and people listened
to them they would not bring a קרבן. korban, Why not? Even
though it has all those components, the קרבן korban you bring, the
individual brings, is an עולה ויורד, oleh ve-yored, is a variable cost
קרבן. korban And since that's the קרבן, korban, the בית דין beis
din only brings their קרבן korban. if the people did a sin
that had the individual done it they would bring a normal
fixed price חטאת. chatas. But a variable price חטאת chatas or whatever
variable type חטאת, chatas, so that's what it says. This is not
the sin a type of a sin, even though it looks like
it's got all the components, that בית דין beis din would be
חייב chayav. for. Okay. So the גמרא gemara says זו היא מצות
עשה שבמקדש שאין חייבין עליה, zo hi mitzvat aseh she-be-mikdash she-ein chayavin
aleha, that you are not, that you are not means that a
בית דין beis din is not חייב chayav for it. So the
גמרא Gemara says היכי קאי, heichi kai, what's the context of this
statement that it says זו היא, zo hi, this is the one?
התם קאי, hatam kai, it's going over there in הוריות. Horayos. אין
חייבין על עשה ועל לא תעשה שבמקדש. ein chayavin al aseh ve-al
lo ta'aseh she-be-mikdash. It's a משנה mishnah in הוריות. Horayos. בית דין
beis din would not bring a קרבן korban, if they ruled incorrectly
about a positive and a negative מצוה mitzvah relating to the טומאה
tumah of the מקדש. mikdash. Even though there's a positive and a
negative and כרית kares and a קרבן, korban but it's not a
fixed price קרבן. korban Okay. Now because it's not a fixed price
קרבן, korban there's another הלכה halachah, as well. If an individual has
a doubt if he did if he or she did something that
would be deserving of a קרבן חטאת, korban chatas, I don't know
if I ate חלב chelev or not, I have a concrete reason
to think I might have, okay, I bring an אשם תלוי, asham
talui, which is a type of a קרבן korban to suspend the
judgment until I can figure out if I did the sin or
not. That אשם תלוי asham talui is only for a sin that
when I discover I've done it, I would bring a fixed price
חטאת. chatas. But a sin like טומאת מקדש, tumat mikdash, that when
I discover I've done it I bring a variable price חטאת, chatas,
there's no אשם תלוי asham talui for it if I have a
doubt whether I've done it. Okay, so that's what it goes on,
this משנה mishnah in הוריות. Horayos. ואין מביאים אשם תלוי על עשה
ועל לא תעשה שבמקדש. ve-ein mevi'im asham talui al aseh ve-al lo
ta'aseh she-be-mikdash. Fine, so that's the context. So that we've done discussing
this whole issue about going into the מקדש mikdash בטומאה be-tumah and
all the various scenarios of the various קרבנות korbanos and יום כיפור
Yom Kippur and ways in which you how long you have to
stay in there etc. and it's not a type of a thing
that a בית דין beis din would bring a קרבן korban, for.
Now that gets us onto another digression which is oh what's the
type of a thing that בית דין beis din would bring a
קרבן korban, for? Now you could probably think about a million things.
Don't eat חלב, chelev, okay, you know that that's a classic example
of bringing a חטאת. chatas. You could even say there's an עשה.
aseh. The עשה aseh is כל בהמה טהורה תאכלו kol behemah tehorah
tocheilu and the לא תעשה lo ta'aseh is like
you know or like what... okay this is not a בהמה טמאה
behemah temeiah but anyway you know
you could probably pick a ton of things
that
בית דין Beis Din would bring a קרבן korban, for, like... You
want to know the type of thing בית דין beis din would
be חייב chayav for if they פסק paskened incorrectly about a case
of a man having sex with a woman when she was a
נדה, niddah, having intercourse with a woman when she was a נדה.
niddah. Okay, and the scenario is is that if he's having intercourse
with her and the intercourse started before she was a נדה niddah
and then in the middle of the intercourse she said, "I just
became a נדה," niddah, he has to withdraw, but it's actually the
exact flip הלכה halachah, of, and it's so fascinating the way the
גמרא Gemara is suggesting or the משנה Mishnah is suggesting all these
parallels. Okay, in this case you're supposed to get out as fast
as possible and not wait, and it's all about שהייה is a
problem, doing as fast as possible is the issue. There, if the
man withdraws while he still has an erection, that's considered part of
the act of intercourse and actually that's a transgression and he actually
has to wait till he loses the erection and then withdraw. So
it's like the exact, I mean, okay, aesthetically, it's funny to use
that word, but anyway, speaking, it's a nice like little parallel, okay?
But it makes all these really interesting suggestions which is very powerful
from the way in, like
religiously, you know, a lot of people think, maybe not so much
in the modern Orthodox community but certainly like in the חרדי Charedi
community about issues around the הלכות halachos of טומאת נדה, tumas niddah,
you know, because on the one hand in the תורה Torah itself,
נדה niddah appears with all the other טומאות, tumos, right? Like with
a זב zav and a זבה zavah and a בעל קרי ba'al
keri and like all those things, right? So to what degree do
we, and the מסכת נדה Maseches Niddah is in מסכת טהרות, Maseches
Taharos, so to what degree do we think about it as just
טומאה וטהרה? tumah v'taharah? On the other hand, there are טומאה וטהרה
tumah v'taharah mostly isn't relevant nowadays, but the one thing that applies,
the one remaining הלכה halachah, of טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah is the
fact that a נדה niddah is not allowed to have, you know,
a נדה niddah can't have sex with her husband, or a man
can't have intercourse with a woman who's a נדה. niddah. Okay, so
it still has that application in terms of that all other areas
of טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah do not. So,
you know, and then there's always the question about are they always
the same consideration? Like there's a couple of הלכות halachos of טומאת
נדה tumas niddah that some ראשונים Rishonim say, "Oh, this only makes
her טמא in terms of issues like the בית המקדש, it wouldn't
affect her status vis-a-vis her husband," which is very bizarre to think
that those two could be separate. Okay, but on the one hand
we're dealing with נדה niddah that is a טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah
idea. There's an idea of, you know, not entering in, you know,
literally, I mean, the act of intercourse is called ביאה. bi'ah. We
just quoted a פסוק, pasuk, הבא אל הבית, habah el habayis, right?
לא יבוא. lo yavo. ביאה bi'ah is the act of intercourse, it's
to penetrate, to enter in from the male perspective, right? So it's
not entering in in a state of טומאה. tumah. Okay, and then
there's a whole issues of if you are טמא, how does one
withdraw? Right? I mean, it's making these exact parallels. But of course
the suggestion then is, if you think about it, oh, but when
there's no טומאה, tumah, if we're going to make that suggestion, then
when there's no טומאה, tumah, then the act of intercourse is being
held up in parallel to the act of entering into the בית
המקדש, right? If you just think about the parallels we've suggested, which
suggests two things. On the one hand, there's very vivid imagery by
the, when the גמרא Gemara discusses how the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
goes into the Holy of Holies on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, that
very vivid imagery in the גמרא Gemara that sort of sees that
as a type of an act of intercourse, like it's the ultimate
intimacy with God. On the other hand, if you think about husband
and wife, you know, to talk about, you know, the קדושה, kedusha,
the sanctity, you know, of the sexual act and the way through
which the sexual act, you know, both husband and wife are coming
together, a baby might be being conceived, you know, and if you
think about, so using that imagery that it's sort of like, you
know, it's being compared to entering into the temple and doing an
act of worship, right? So there's like, it's very powerful what those
ideas are, you know? And that's why in a lot of like,
you know, traditional literature the talk is about קדושת ישראל Kedushas Yisrael
is dependent on keeping טהרת המשפחה. taharas hamishpacha. So you get the
word טהרה taharah like in הלכות נדה, hilchos niddah, right? And it's
קדושת ישראל Kedushas Yisrael because this is where the Jewish babies are
formed in this union and this is where we still have
like קדושה kedusha nowadays. So this whole parallel and imagery is extremely
powerful. All right, so let's see now what the גמרא says. All
right, so it says, אבל חייבין על עשה ולא תעשה שבנדה. aval
chayavin al assei v'lo sa'assei she'be'niddah. So the thing you would be
חייב chayav for, the בית דין Beit Din would be, is if
they ruled about the positive and negative commands of a נדה niddah
incorrectly and then this person wound up having intercourse or withdrawing when
he still had an erection and that's why he transgressed. ומביא אשם
תלוי על עשה ולא תעשה שבנדה, u'meivi asham talui al assei v'lo
sa'assei she'be'niddah, similarly if there was a doubt about it, he'd bring
an אשם תלוי. asham talui. זו היא מצות עשה שבמקדש, zohi mitzvas
assei she'be'mikdash, so our משנה Mishnah was saying, this issue about going
in and staying. getting whatever in the בית המקדש שאין חייבין עליה
she’ein chayavin aleha is one that a בית דין Beit Din would
not be חייב if it ruled, ואיזו היא מצות עשה שבנידה שחייבין
עליה v’eizu hi mitzvat aseh shebeniddah shechayavin aleha which is one that
you are חייב is the following and this is now our משנה,
Mishnah, which is this is the parallel to the מקדש Mikdash case,
but this is the case that בית דין would transgress cause it
is כרת and you do bring a חטאת chatat if it was
בשוגג. beshogeg. היה משמש עם הטהורה, haya meshamesh im hatehorah, a man
was having intercourse with a woman who was not a נידה, niddah,
ואמרה לו נטמאתי, v’amra lo nitmeiti, a man was having intercourse with
a woman who was not a נידה niddah and then she says
I became a נידה. niddah. ופירש מיד ufiresh miyad and he separated
immediately while he still had an erection, so חייב, he is חייב,
that’s an act of having intercourse, that’s considered an act of intercourse
and that would be an act of כרת if it was בשוגג,
beshogeg, he didn’t realize that it was forbidden or whatever, it would
bring a חטאת. chatat. Okay, and that’s חייב. The לא תעשה lo
ta’aseh is not having intercourse with a woman who is a נידה,
niddah, and the עשה aseh is, we’re going to learn from a
minute, והזרתם את בני ישראל מטומאתם. v’hizartem et bnei yisrael mitumatom. We’re
going to learn from a פסוק pasuk of a positive מצוה mitzvah
that you should have to be separate in these type cases, you
know, similar to וישלחו מן המחנה, v’yishalchu min hamachaneh, you have to
separate in order to make sure you do not become טמא. מפני
שיציאתו הנאה לו כביאתו mipnei sheyetz’iato hana’ah lo k’bi’ato and the reason
it’s transgressive if he withdraws immediately is because it’s the same pleasure,
it’s part of the act of intercourse, we know, the movement in
and the movement out. איתמר, itmar, now, it was taught. אביי אמר
משמיה דרבי חייא בר רב, Abaye amar mishmeih d’Rabbi Chiya bar Rav,
חייב שתים. chayav shtayim. If a man withdraws while he has an
erection, he transgresses the, he starts having sex and then he withdraws
and then he became a נידה niddah in the middle, he transgresses
twice. וכן אמר רבא אמר רב שמואל בר רב שבא אמר רב
הונא, v’chein amar Rava amar Rav Shmuel bar Rav Shava amar Rav
Huna, חייב שתים, chayav shtayim, חייב twice. חד אכניסה, chad achneisah, one
for having done the intercourse initially. Now, the funny thing is when
he did the initial act of intercourse she wasn’t yet a נידה,
niddah, she became a נידה niddah during, you know, in the during,
so how he gets for that initial act? וחד אפרישה v’chad afreishah
and one on withdrawing. So we get the withdrawing, we don’t get
the initial act. Okay, so we are going to, I guess, let’s
finish the דף, daf, we’ll probably wind up repeating this tomorrow, but
let’s just read to the end of the דף. daf. So הוי
בה רבא, havei bah Rava, so Rabbah or Rava, like, challenged this
or, like, questioned this. במאי, bemai, what’s the scenario? אילימא סמוך לווסתה,
eillima samuch l’vestah, if you say the reason he transgressed for the
original act before she was a נידה niddah was because she was
right, was right before she was expected to get her period. So
that’s like being highly irresponsible, right? So that’s, you know, you do
not go ahead and do something if there’s a good likelihood that
in the process of doing it, it’s going to turn into be
an עבירה. aveirah. All right? So that’s why, now he’s not מזיד,
meyzid, but he would be, let’s say, you know, he would be
like a שוגג, shogeg, he would think that it wouldn’t, he told
himself it wasn’t going to happen maybe or he thought that he
would, you know, be very quick, you know, type of a thing.
So okay, but it’s still irresponsible and you’d bring a חטאת. chatat.
So if that’s the scenario, ובמאי, ubemai, now who are we talking
about? אילימא בתלמיד חכם, eillima b’talmid chacham, somebody who’s a scholar. So
therefore he knows what the הלכות halachot are. בשלמא אכניסה ליחייב, bishlama
achneisah lichayev, I get why he’s חייב for the initial act of
penetration because that was a שוגג shogeg and קסבר יכולני לבעול, kasavar
yacholni liv’ol, he figures I can have, do an act of intercourse
with my wife and we can separate before she gets her period.
Okay, he was irresponsible but he wasn’t intentional. So that’s why he
brings one קרבן, korban. that I get. אלא אפרישה אמאי חייב, ela
afreishah amai chayav, but by פרישה, perishah, when he separates, why is
he חייב a קרבן, korban. meaning it’s not that he should be
off the hook, he’s more transgressing. If he knows the הלכה, then
when he separates and he withdraws, he’s מזיד meyzid now, he’s willful.
Okay, so if he knows what he’s doing, then he’s negligent at
the beginning, that’s a קרבן, korban, but he’s willful at the end,
that’s not a קרבן. korban, Okay. And we’ll just do one more
line, while we’ll review this tomorrow, but we’ll read one more line.
אי בעם הארץ, ei b’am ha’aretz, and if the guy doesn’t know
הלכה, so אידי ואידי אהדא שגגה דחדא דלמא הוה, idai v’idai ahada
shegagah d’chada delma havah, so,
so then it’s all one state of not knowing. Okay, even when
he finds out in the middle, oh, you know, his wife tells
him in the middle, oh, you know what, I just became a
נידה, niddah, the way רש"י explains it is he doesn’t realize that
he’s now done anything wrong because he didn’t realize that it was
wrong to be having sex in the, you know, having intercourse in
the first place when she was about to get her period. So
the only, so it’s like it’s all one big act of one
big mistake. I’ll explain this more tomorrow. But the basic point is
since he’s pretty ignorant in general of the הלכה, so it would
not lead to two קרבנות. korbanot. One being aware in the middle
that she became a נידה niddah doesn’t make him aware that he’s
done anything wrong and doesn’t make him aware that he has to
bring a קרבן. korban So therefore, even though he did two separate
things that were wrong and neither of them were intentional and both
of them were בשוגג, beshogeg, one was he started having intercourse with
his wife right before she became a, you know, a נידה niddah
and the other was he withdrew while he still had the erection,
because he never became fully aware in the middle. but he was
obligated in a קרבן, it would only be one קרבן, not two
קרבנות. korbanot. So we will continue this tomorrow, but I do need
to end by saying of course this complete thing is all male
from the male perspective, androcentric, I mean even to the point that
we're talking about the קרבנות korbanot that he has to bring and
not the קרבנות korbanot that she has to bring. You know, she
also is doing the act. You know, so maybe she's not controlling
whether he's withdrawing with or without his erection, but she's also obligated
in a קרבן for engaging in the act initially. Okay, so the
whole thing is of course going to be very male perspective, but
we will continue with this on שבת. Shabbos. Yes. Question? They seem
to be using the term עם הארץ am ha'aretz more in the
way that it is used